<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
  "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
  <meta charset="UTF-8" />

  <title>What online gaming taught me about startups</title>
  <meta name="description" content="" />
</head>

<body>

<div id="content">
  
    <h2>What online gaming taught me about startups</h2>

  <p><img alt="" src="../Images/4565561717_2207e64f9f.jpg"/></p><p>Whilst researching for the <a href="http://joel.is/post/22436341176/achieving-overnight-success-kevin-systrom">Achieving overnight success: Kevin Systrom</a> piece I published two weeks ago, I was excited to see that one of Systrom’s earliest recollections of something that impacted his journey with startups was that he played Doom II a lot:</p><p>"That was how I got into it actually. I’ll credit Doom II for everything."<br/>- Kevin Systrom</p><p>I got really into online games when I was around 11, and there were a few things from the experience which I seem oddly similar to lessons I’ve learned doing startups in the last few years:</p><p>When I got into online gaming it was a fairly small game which got me hooked. I played more popular games like Age of Empires and CouterStrike, but it was a simple racing game called Midtown Madness 2 with a small audience that captured my attention. I can remember there were only ever around 300 people online, and after a while I knew almost all of them. When I got involved in the community and formed my own team, since there were not many people we were able to dominate.</p><p>Over a decade later whilst journeying into the world of startups, I initially tried to make a product work immediately in a large market with <a href="http://myonepage.com">OnePage</a>, “your business card in the cloud”. It was when I switched my efforts to build <a href="http://bufferapp.com">Buffer</a>, a product with a seemingly smaller audience that I had much more success.</p><p>In Midtown Madness 2, there were many different game modes: “circuits”, “checkpoint”, “blitz” and “cops n robbers”. When I  started my own team, I started with just a few friends and we only competed in “cops n robbers” games. Even within this, there were people who would compete with just a specific vehicle. That’s how we began, and we became very good at that single type of game. Eventually, we expanded to all “cops n robbers” vehicles and eventually all game types. It was much easier to expand to others and attract more players by starting strong in one area.</p><p>I made many mistakes whilst spending a year and a half on my previous startup, and during that period I read a lot about the <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/">lean startup</a> concept. Today, Buffer has a whole host of features and integrations. However, when I first launched, it was only available as a queue to delay Tweets for a single Twitter account. This proved to be a good approach, and it was easier to choose the best next steps once I had usage. This is similar to the <a href="http://cdixon.org/2010/08/21/the-bowling-pin-strategy/">bowling pin strategy</a> and I believe it’s key to triggering initial traction.</p><p>When I started playing Midtown Madness 2, I had no idea that teams even existed and how people came together at certain times to play regularly. I didn’t know all the language people were using, and I was constantly called a ‘noob’. When I had my own team and realised it’d be useful to have a website, I had no idea how to build one. Eventually though this is how I learned HTML, CSS, JavaScript and PHP which are the very skills I’ve used to build a high growth and profitable startup.</p><p>With <a href="http://bufferapp.com">Buffer</a>, neither me nor my co-founder <a href="http://twitter.com/tommoor">Tom</a> had done much sysadmin work before we started. However, when we began gaining traction we had to learn how to scale up the technology. I barely knew what a database index was at the start, but now we have 10 servers with database replication and load-balancing. If there’s any one thing that’s helped me, it’s a belief that whilst I don’t know what I need to know right now, I know I will be able to learn it or talk to the right people for help.</p><p>I was a real geek. I got completely obsessed with Midtown Madness 2, and whilst other kids were playing out in the street I was playing the game online with friends I had never met. I would play for hours on end, and I also spent hours coding the website for the team I had created. I spent probably two full years in this state of obsession, and eventually we competed for cash prizes and had some success.</p><p>In my article on <a href="http://joel.is/post/22436341176/achieving-overnight-success-kevin-systrom">Kevin Systrom’s “overnight success”</a>, I attempted to validate through research my assumption that in fact it takes a huge amount of time to succeed in a big way with startups. Looking back at my own journey with startups, it actually started all the way back with gaming, since that’s how I learned to code. I’ve also spent almost two years on my previous unsuccessful startup before <a href="http://bufferapp.com">Buffer</a>. Even with Buffer, we’ve now been running for one and a half years and we still feel like we’re just getting started.</p><p>Are there any experiences in childhood that have some correlation to things you have found to work today? I’d love to hear from you in the comments.</p><p>Photo credit: <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/futurilla/4565561717/">Futurilla</a></p>
</div>

</body>
</html>